- Arthur C. Clarke had a sequel
to "2001, A Space Odyssey."
It's called "2010, Odyssey Two."
And at the end of it,
an alien intelligence
converts Jupiter into a star.
As a group of astronauts
narrowly escape the implosion,
they receive the following
message from the aliens,
"All these worlds are
yours, except Europa,
attempt no landing there."
Now that was just a novel, but it suggests
that already in 1982,
we suspected that Europa
might offer our best chance
of finding alien life in the solar system.
42 years later, in October 2024,
NASA is actually launching
the most advanced mission
to hunt for signs of alien life.
And it's going to Jupiter's moon Europa.
There's just one problem,
Jupiter kills everything around it.
So how could life exist there?
And how do you make a probe
that can withstand the
perilous conditions?
(suspenseful music)
(gentle music)
Deep inside Jupiter,
there is so much pressure,
that hydrogen is believed to take the form
of a metallic liquid.
And this metallic liquid
hydrogen generates
an incredibly powerful magnetic field,
almost 20,000 times stronger than Earth,
if you measure at the same distance away.
So if you could see this
magnetic field from Earth,
it would appear twice
as big as the full moon.
On its own, that magnetic
field is harmless.
But right in the middle of it
is the most volcanically active
world in the solar system,
Jupiter's moon, Io.
The volcanoes on Io's
surface shoot out tons
of sulfur dioxide, and every second,
one ton of this material gets ionized
and trapped inside
Jupiter's magnetic field.
And the field accelerates these particles
to rotate incredibly fast with Jupiter.
So they whizz around at over
300 kilometers per second.
Their inertia actually
pulls back on the field,
stretching it out.
And this trapped material
slams into other moons,
ejecting even more particles
from their surfaces.
This cycle forms massive radiation belts
which span past Europa and
the other moons of Jupiter.
Now, for electronics, this
intense radiation is kryptonite.
In the 1970s, the Pioneer
10 and Voyager missions
only briefly passed by Jupiter,
but the radiation caused glitches,
gave the instruments false commands,
and corrupted some of their data.
Even with modern shielding,
a spacecraft within the radiation belts
would only survive for
around three months.
So how will NASA's new
mission, the Europa Clipper,
orbit Europa for over four
years without getting fried?
Well, the solution is, it won't.
It'll orbit Jupiter from afar
and then swoop in every few
weeks to quickly fly by Europa
and then leave again.
And since the mission is going
to collect a lot of data,
it can use the downtime
while it's way out here
to transmit it all back to Earth
before going in for another swoop.
In all, it'll do 49 flybys,
mapping almost the entire surface.
That's actually how the
Clipper got its name,
after the fast and nimble
19th century Clipper ships,
quickly dipping in and out of ports.
But of all the places in the solar system
to look for life, why Europa?
If you stood on Europa's surface,
you'd be hit with 5,400 milliSieverts
of radiation in a single day.
That's 1,800 times more than
the annual dose here on Earth.
If you stay here for a couple of hours,
you would eventually die
from radiation sickness.
But Europa contains a secret.
When Voyager 1 passed by Jupiter in 1979,
it took this photo of Europa.
If you compare it to
most of the other moons
in the solar system,
you'll notice something
is missing, craters.
Every planet and moon has been bombarded
by asteroids over billions of years.
And most planetary surfaces show it.
But not Europa.
So why not?
Well, something recent,
say over the last 60 million years or so,
must have been happening on Europa
to erase most of these
craters from the surface.
16 years after Voyager,
Galileo arrived to Jupiter.
It spent eight years
studying both the gas giant
and its moons.
And Galileo's magnetometer
picked up something interesting on Europa.
Jupiter's magnetic poles, like Earth's,
aren't aligned with its geographic poles.
So as the planet rotates every 10 hours,
the whole magnetic field wobbles.
This changing field from Jupiter
induces a magnetic field on Europa,
and a relatively strong one at that.
That means there must be an
electrically conductive layer
within Europa that reacts
to Jupiter's field.
And readings from Galileo indicate
that it must be somewhere
close to the surface,
only 10s of kilometers deep.
So what kind of conductive layer?
Well, Europa's white surface
is almost entirely covered
in a thick crust of water ice.
These reddish-brown regions,
when observed through a spectrometer,
fit the description of a lot
of things, like hydrated salts,
sulfuric acid or even bacteria.
We need more data to be sure,
but recent experiments at
JPL found that sea salt
when bombarded with intense radiation,
turns from white
to this same brownish
color found on Europa.
So scientists suspect
that there's a whole
saltwater ocean inside Europa
that could be 100 kilometers deep.
Meaning that Europa would
contain twice as much water
as the whole of the Earth.
And it must driving geological activity
that constantly smooths out
and renews the surface of the moon.
But the Jupiter system only gets about 4%
of the sunlight we get here on Earth.
So Europa's surface is constantly
below -160 deg Celsius,
so you'd expect the
ocean to be frozen solid.
But there's a way to generate heat
that doesn't rely on the Sun.
And I've got a little
demo here to prove it.
Europa's orbit around Jupiter
isn't a perfect circle.
This is because Io, Europa and Ganymede
are in orbital resonance.
Each time Ganymede completes one orbit,
Europa completes two and Io four.
Because of that, Io tugs Europa inward
on one side of the orbit,
while Ganymede pulls it out on the other,
making its orbit more eccentric.
Now, Jupiter's pull is stronger
on the closer side of the
orbit than on the farther side.
So Europa is constantly
being stretched and squeezed,
stretched and squeezed.
And you can see how this
rubber ball gets warmer
as I squeeze it.
Scientists believe that
the friction caused
by the tidal flexing of the entire moon
can generate enough heat
to keep the ocean liquid.
This effect gets stronger the
closer you are to Jupiter,
which is why Io is so volcanically active.
So you can see this ball is
significantly hotter now.
I held onto this ball at the same time
to make sure that it wasn't
just the heat coming in
from my hand.
What sort of temperature of
the ocean are we thinking?
- So it depends on how salty it is.
So, melting temperature of ice
or maybe depressed by 10
degrees Celsius below that
if it's a very salty ocean.
Similar to cold oceans on Earth.
- And how would the flexing differ
if there's this big liquid ocean
versus if there's no ocean there?
- If there's no ocean, Europa should flex
by only about one meter in amplitude.
But if there's an ocean in there,
then it flexes with an
amplitude of 30 meters.
So that's an enormous deflection.
And that will come out pretty
clearly in the gravity data.
Another argument for how
thick the ice shell is,
we see these very strange
features on the surface
that are arcuate in shape,
but like multiple arcs put together.
We call them cycloids.
Not something you'd expect
to see on an icy moon.
And we think they form
if a crack propagates
at just the right speed, about
the speed someone would walk,
and is following the changing stress field
of Europa being squeezed as
it orbits around Jupiter.
And if there were no ocean down there,
there wouldn't be enough of
an amplitude of that motion
to explain the cracking.
But if there is an ocean,
then it could explain the cracking.
- All that tidal flexing pushes
magma in the outer core up,
closer to the seafloor.
Water flowing through the
crust above it is heated
and it picks up minerals from the ground,
ejecting them into the ocean.
This creates hydrothermal vents.
And where we find these on
Earth, we also find life.
Thousands of meters below the
surface, with no sunlight,
these vents are oases for ocean life.
The lifeforms down here
rely on unique bacteria,
bacteria that feed on the
minerals from the vents,
rather than on the energy
provided by the Sun.
How long are we thinking
that Europa has had an ocean?
- It could be four billion
years, we don't know for sure.
- That amount of time could
give life the opportunity
to evolve in those oceans?
- Right, exactly right.
Organisms can use methane,
carbon dioxide, sulfur reactions.
Any chemical reaction you can think of
that might happen in the
ocean can potentially be used
as a fuel for that organism's metabolism.
So we're not talking about
searching for fishes,
or whales or squids or
something down there,
but looking for single cell organisms.
- We were so concerned there
might be life on Europa that,
when the Galileo mission
was ending in 2003,
it was deliberately crashed into Jupiter
to avoid the risk of contaminating Europa.
But Clipper will not be able
to drill through the
kilometers-thick ice crust.
So how are we going to find evidence
for life beneath that thick surface?
This is the SnotBot.
It's a drone with Petri
dishes glued to the top,
and it flies right through whale blows
to collect whale snot right here on Earth.
And zoologists can use the SnotBot
to retrieve all sorts of
info on a whale's biology.
And it turns we can do
something very similar
for celestial bodies too.
We've actually captured images
of water geysers shooting
out of Enceladus,
a moon of Saturn, housing
a subsurface ocean.
And the Hubble space telescope
has picked up some evidence
of what could be similar
geyser eruptions on Europa.
The hope is that Clipper
could fly through one
of these plumes, like the SnotBot,
and reveal their chemical composition
using a mass spectrometer.
But evidence for an ocean
on Europa isn't conclusive.
Enceladus seems like a stronger candidate,
we have actual images of its plumes
and we've even flown through them.
We are almost 100% certain
there's a subsurface ocean there.
If we have these plumes on Enceladus
and there's clearly maybe
a liquid ocean there,
why does Europa have your
attention more than Enceladus?
Is there something that draws you?
- We don't know how long
it takes life to get going,
but it's possible that Enceladus
may have just kind of
started up its engines,
whereas Europa has more
likely been well evolved
over a long time.
- Surprisingly, being bombarded
by Jupiter's radiation
actually makes Europa a better candidate.
See, those high-speed particles
hitting Europa's surface
give water and carbon dioxide
molecules enough energy
to form new compounds,
like formaldehyde or hydrogen peroxide.
And these can serve as food
for life beneath the surface,
if they can get down that far.
- And we have evidence of
overturn of the icy shell
at chaos zones where the icy
crust seems to have collided
and material has been
shoved into the icy shell.
So there may be ways
for this fuel for life
to get down into the icy shell
and potentially to the ocean.
- [Derek] And Clipper
doesn't have to touch down
on the surface to confirm this.
- There's an infrared spectrometer
to look at the chemical fingerprints
of light bounced off the
surface to help identify
and map out where the salts are,
find if there are organics there.
There is an ultraviolet spectrograph
that's aboard the spacecraft
to look for plumes.
Are they there?
And of course, then can
we fly through them?
And then there'll be imaging
of essentially the whole globe
at better than 100 meters
per pixel resolution.
So one camera will take swaths of images
as we fly over the surface
and that's called the wide angle camera.
And then the other camera
is the narrow angle camera.
From 50 kilometers altitude,
it will get half meter
per pixel images, right?
So it'll be able to resolve my desk here
if it were on Europa.
And then it would be a future mission,
like a lander that would go
and actually search for
signs of life on Europa.
- Do you think a lander would
have a chance of survival?
- There have been studies
that say we can get a lander living
on the surface for a month.
If we think that's
sufficient to go in there,
scoop some stuff up from below the depth
of radiation processing,
and put it into a mass
spectrometer and see what we see.
- But the Europa Clipper
won't be studying Jupiter's moons alone.
The European Space Agency's JUICE mission,
or the Jupiter Icy Moon Explorer,
is already on its way to Jupiter.
It will come to the system
just 15 months after Clipper
and it'll even be doing
a few flybys of Europa,
before settling into a
tight orbit around Ganymede.
So the European Space Agency
will also have a mission
there at the same time?
- Yes, we're having informal conversations
with members of the JUICE science team.
What would it mean to
have two spacecraft there
at the same time?
The JUICE mission will end
up in orbit around Ganymede
and Ganymede has its own magnetosphere.
Well, we'll be outside
Ganymede's magnetosphere.
So we might say, "Oh, look,
there's this big burst
coming from Jupiter."
And then JUICE might say,
"Oh, we felt that over here
in our magnetic signals."
So we wouldn't have to
really do anything different
except talk to each other
and make sure that the sum of the whole
is even bigger than its parts.
- Europa Clipper was scheduled to launch
on October 10, 2024,
but NASA is waiting for
Hurricane Milton to clear Florida
before the spacecraft can take off safely.
When will we get the first results?
- You'll start seeing distant
observations coming in in 2030
as we look at Europa from
afar and search for plumes.
And then you'll see the first
really high resolution data
in 2031.
- So after say 26 years of thinking
about a mission to Europa,
how does it feel to be so close to launch?
- It's a little surreal,
(laughs) I must say.
This has been such a long time coming.
It's occasionally hitting
me that our spacecraft
is going to be up there in the
heavens, right, on its way.
It turns out that, during a Europa Ocean Conference
in the late 1990s,
NASA actually video-called
Arthur C. Clarke.
And after showing him plans
for a future mission
to explore the faraway ocean world,
Clarke finally gave NASA
permission to land on Europa.
(monitor whooshing)
Europa Clipper is a perfect example
of the amazing things we can do
when we set ourselves ambitious goals
and work together with
others to achieve them.
But I think we often get
wrapped up in our everyday lives
and forget just how much
of an impact we can make on the world.
That's true on a society-wide level,
like these big international
space missions,
but I also think it's true
at an individual level.
You yourself can probably
accomplish much more
than you think when it comes
to making the world a better place.
And today's sponsor, 80,000 Hours,
wants to help you do just that.
They're not selling anything.
80,000 Hours is a nonprofit
that can help you work out
a plan for achieving a big,
positive impact in the world,
and then executing on it.
Career advice typically
aims to help you find a job
that suits your preferences.
But what if you really care
about helping the world?
Well sure, they can tell you
to be a doctor or a teacher,
but these aren't your only options.
Which is why 80,000 Hours
have done over 10 years of research
into how to find a career
that does a lot of good,
and also feels satisfying.
They have everything from
an in-depth career guide,
to a podcast on the world's
most pressing problems
and how we can solve them.
They even have a curated job board
with hundreds of high-impact
career opportunities.
And everything they
provide is free, forever.
So if you want to make a difference
with the 80,000 hours you
have to shape your career,
then sign up now at
80000hours.org/veritasium.
There's a link in the description
or you can scan this QR code.
So, I want to thank 80,000
Hours for sponsoring this video,
and I want to thank you for watching.